Guide to the North African Jewish Manuscript Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Tafilalt, 1767-1981; Series VI
  - Letter in Judeo-Arabic written by Avraham Ben-Harosh to his parents in Israel while he still lived in Morocco, 1953; MS.1825.1009; 4 pages; 22 centimeters. (Box 16, Folder 22)
    Place: Qaṣr al-Sūq. The letter was written in Qaṣr al-Sūq by Avraham Ben-Harosh to his father and mother, Aharon and Ester Ben-Harosh, who immigrated to Israel in 1951. The letter deals with personal matters and with a quarrel that Aharon had with a family member. The letter also conveys messages on behalf of Aharon's two daughters-in-law, Sarah (Avraham's wife) and Zohara (David's wife), and his youngest daughter, Yakut. The letter also mentions a legal document to be sent from the rabbi of Qaṣr al-Sūq, Avraham Lasri, to Aharon in Israel. David added a short note at the bottom of the letter.
  - Letter sent by Shimon Attia in Morocco to his daughter Sarah and son-in-law Avraham Ben-Harosh in Israel, regarding his sorrow at being apart from them, 1956; MS.1825.1010; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 16, Folder 22)
    Place: Qaṣr al-Sūq. Shimon Attia from Qaṣr al-Sūq sent the letter to his daughter, Sarah, and to his son-in-law, Avraham Ben-Harosh. The letter deals with the pain caused by the separation after the two immigrated to Israel. The letter mentions financial support provided by Shimon to his son Ena (Masud) and a memorial service that Shimon held for another son, Shalom. The letter includes an apology by Yaakov Shitrit (the person who wrote the letter) for not taking the time to say farewell to Avraham Ben-Harosh before his departure to Israel. The letter is written in Judeo-Arabic.
  - Legal document written by Avraham Ben-Harosh on behalf of a blind relative, 1981; MS.1825.1011; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. (Box 16, Folder 22)
    Place: Jerusalem. The document, dated 25 Adar II 5741 (March 1981), was written by Avraham Ben-Harosh upon the request of his nephew, Avraham Attia. Avraham Attia donated a Torah scroll and appointed Avraham Ben-Harosh to take care of the arrangements for placing the Torah scroll in a synagogue. Since Attia was blind, the document has his finger print in place of a signature. Avraham Attia died on 27 Tishre 5742 (Oct. 1981) and the Torah scroll was placed in his memory in a synagogue in Jerusalem.
  - Report by Avraham Ben-Harosh on the proofreading of a Torah scroll, 1956; MS.1825.1012; 4 columns (1 blank); 28 centimeters. (Box 16, Folder 23)
    Place: Israel. Avraham Ben-Harosh, who was an expert Torah scribe, was asked to proofread a Torah scroll from Romania that was to be donated to a synagogue in a refugee absorption camp. In this report he recorded the 34 errors and imperfections that he corrected.
  - Sharḥ Parashat Bereshit, Circa 1960s; MS.1825.1013; 2 leaves; 31 centimeters. (Box 16, Folder 23)
    Place: Israel. Translation of the beginning portion of the Book of Genesis into Judeo-Arabic according to the tradition of Tafilalt. Avraham Ben-Harosh wrote down this translation in the 1960's. He had taught this material as a teacher in the religious school of the large synagogue in Qaṣr al-Sūq in the Tafilalt region in the 1930's.
  - Sharḥ Yonah, Circa 1950s; MS.1825.1014; 4 pages; 20 centimeters. (Box 16, Folder 23)
    Place: Tafilalt. Translation of the Book of Jonah by Avraham Ben-Harosh into Judeo-Arabic according to the tradition of Tafilalt. It includes the additional verses appended to the Book of Jonah in the haftarah of Yom Kippur afternoon.
  - Description by Avraham Ben-Harosh of a wedding ceremony according to the custom of Tafilalt, Circa 1940-circa 1960; MS.1825.1015; 2 pages; 24 centimeters. (Box 16, Folder 23)
    Place: Tafilalt. The document is written in Hebrew and includes Aramaic elements and terms that originated in the Arabic language.
  - Collection of texts copied by Avraham Ben-Harosh, 1929; MS.1825.1018; 406 pages; 22 centimeters. (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Place: Boudenib. Poems and elegies, biblical commentary, and discussions of Jewish law, particularly related to laws of kosher slaughtering. Copied in Boudenib, Tafilalt by Avraham Ben-Harosh. A colophon, page 192a, contains the signature of Avraham Ben-Harosh, as well as the letters indicating the Hebrew year 5630. According to his son Moshe Bar-Asher, this book was most likely copied before the month of Kislev when his father received his semikhah (rabbinic ordination), hence the date 1929 for this manuscript. Among the important contents of this manuscript are: an authentic version of the laws of kosher slaughtering by Refael Berdugo (pages 142-192); a short text concerning laws of kosher slaughtering with interpretations based on numeric values of letters (page 193b); a long poem summarizing laws of kosher slaughtering by an author using the pseudonym "Shemaʻ Shelomoh" (pages 194-203); the lamentation, "El mekudash," one version in Hebrew and a different version written in Arabic in Hebrew letters by Maseod ben Jacob Abihatzera (1834 or 1835-1908), the father of the Baba Sali, Yisrael Abiḥatsira; original lamentations of Yahya Dahan composed after the governor of Tafilalt executed his cousin, the chief rabbi David Abiḥatsira in 1919 (pages 111a-122a); at least ten other texts in Judeo-Arabic recounting the stories of biblical figures such as Job, Moses, and Jospeh; the tale of Sulika, a women killed when she refused to marry an Arab nobleman; and the haftarah of Tisha B'Av. Manuscript in Hebrew, Judeo-Arabic, and Arabic in Hebrew letters.
  - Amulets and folk-remedies from Tafilalt, Circa 1900-circa 1920?; MS.1825.1065; 1 v., charts, 23.centimeters. (Box 17, Folder 2)
    Place: Tafilalt. Contains folk-remedies for a variety of ailments such as toothache - page 2, heart problems - page 2, intestinal problems - page 2, mental illness - page 9, scorpion bites - page 9 and fever - fever - page 9. The manuscript also contains amulets. Manuscript in Hebrew and Arabic.
  - Pitron halomot: manuscript concerning interpretation of dreams, Circa 1900-circa 1920?; MS.1825.1066; 62 pages: charts, 21 centimeters. (Box 17, Folder 3)
    Place: Tafilalt. Unique manuscript in Hebrew concerning interpretation of dreams. Also includes amulets. The manuscript was repaired and bound recently with some pages out of order.
  - Manuscript of amulets written by Makhluf Lasri, Circa 1880-circa 1900; MS.1825.1067; 17 pages; 23 centimeters. Contemporary binding. 10 small unbound sheets inserted in back of book. (Box 17, Folder 4)
    Place: Tafilalt. The manuscript was copied in the Tafilalt region. It includes the texts of amulets as well as directions for folk-remedies to heal a variety of afflictions.
  - Letter in Judeo-Arabic and Hebrew, 1915; MS.1825.1118; 2 pages; 11 centimeters. (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Place: Tafilalt. According to the names and nicknames in the document and on its verso the letter comes from Tafilalt.
  - Letter in North African Judeo-Arabic regarding sale of land, 1934; MS.1825.1297; 1 leaf; 15 x 19 centimeters. (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Place: Qaṣr al-Sūq. Shalom ben Yahya Ben Shitrit sold land to Adi Ben Bahi, the governor of Krando.
  - Document regarding a will, 1934; MS.1825.1513; 4 pages (3 blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Place: Ferkla. The document is from Ferkla, a small village with a Jewish population of about 100. The document is signed by Shelomoh Biton.
- Essaouira, 1844-1957; Series VII
  The documents in Series VII come from Essaouira, also known as Mogador, a city on the coast of the Atlantic Ocean in southern Morocco. Essaouira was established only a few hundred years ago yet became a thriving cosmopolitan community of scholars and merchants. This series includes many documents of the rabbinical court of Essaouira. These include testimony and legal documents concerning individuals, real estate, finances and inheritance as well as a collection of traditional ballads from Essaouira.
  - Series of ballads in High Muslim Arabic, Circa 1900-circa 1920; MS.1825.0017; 128 pages; 33 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Place: Mazagan. Notebook containing a series of kasidot (a form of poetry/ballads) in High Muslim Arabic written in Hebrew script by Mosheh ben Shitrit, the father of Meir ben Shitrit from Essaouira. Although this manuscript was written in Mazagan, the kasidot originate in Essaouira. Most of these poems have not been published. The book and the handwriting are very similar to that of the teacher's notebook, MS.1825.0016.
  - Document concerning a loan, 1872; MS.1825.0043; 4 pages (3 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 2)
    Place: Essaouira. A legal document concerning a loan of money. Signed by the rabbis Yaakov ben Attar and Mosheh [Nahon?].
  - Two documents concerning an incident involving forged documents used to claim the inheritance of orphans, 1880; MS.1825.0069.1-.2; 4 pages; 37 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 2)
    Place: Essaouira. The first document is a rabbinic decision concerning documents presented to a rabbinic tribunal that were written by a scribe who was known to forge documents. The case involved an inheritance designated for orphans for which there were competing claims. The rabbis record here the testimony of three people. Even though the document is written in Hebrew, the testimony is written in both Hebrew and Arabic (essentially Judeo-Arabic, but including many Hebrew terms). The document is signed by Yehudah ben Moyal, Tishre 5641 (probably September 1880). The decision of Yehudah ben Moyal was confirmed by the rabbinic tribunal of Marrakech later that year and again in 1881 by the tribunal of Mordekhai Bengio from Tangier. The document includes names of several towns such as Tamaliht, Nūn Wadi, and Iliah, and also all the names of the witnesses and the forger. It is interesting to see how the rabbis searched for anything in favor of the scribe to avoid declaring him a criminal scribe. The second page is quite similar and concerns the same incident. The main difference is that the second document focuses somewhat more on the reputation and actions of the scribe than the situation of the orphans.
  - Legal decisions from the rabbinical court of Essaouira, 1941; MS.1825.0256.1-.3; 12 pages (8 blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Legal decisions from the rabbinical court of Essaouira, 1942; MS.1825.0257.1-.5; 10 pages (3 blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Legal decisions from the rabbinical court of Essaouira, 1944; MS.1825.0258.01-.21; 42 pages (8 blank); various sizes (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Legal decisions from the rabbinical court of Essaouira, 1947; MS.1825.0259.01-.20; 40 pages (18 blank); various sizes (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Legal decisions from the rabbinical court of Essaouira, 1948; MS.1825.0260.01-.66; 132 pages (61 blank); various sizes (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Legal decisions from the rabbinical court of Essaouira, 1949; MS.1825.0261.01-.33; 66 pages (31 blank); various sizes (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Legal decisions from the rabbinical court of Essaouira, 1952; MS.1825.0262.01-.17; 34 pages (8 blank); various sizes (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Legal decisions from the rabbinical court of Essaouira, 1953; MS.1825.0263.1-.8; 16 pages (1 blank); 21-25 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Legal decisions from the rabbinical court of Essaouira, 1956, 1957; MS.1825.0264.1-.2; 4 pages (1 blank); 25 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Legal decision from the rabbinical court of Essaouira, 1928; MS.1825.0265; 1 leaf; 21 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Recommendation of Shelomoh ha-Kohen Skali as an emissary of the Maghrebi community, 1934 or 1935; MS.1825.0430; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. with tears and some loss of text. (Box 18, Folder 12)
    Place: Essaouira. Recommendation of Shelomoh ha-Kohen Skali, called Zaguri, who is taking the place of Amram Aburabia as the emissary of the Maghrebi community. Signed by David Knafo and Mosheh ben Simhon. Stamped with the seal of the rabbinic court of Essaouira.
  - Document from rabbis of Essaouira regarding real estate, 1875; MS.1825.0506; 4 pages (3 blank); 30 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 12)
    Place: Essaouira. Signed by Shelomoh Shoshan and Mordekhai Altit.
  - Responsum and legal decision from Essaouira, Circa 1850-circa 1900; MS.1825.0697; 16 pages (8 blank); 22 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 13)
    Place: Essaouira. The document mentions a woman from the city of Tangier.
  - Testimony with regard to the identity and age of Meir Hadida from Mogador, 1924; MS.1825.0796; 2 pages; 25 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 14)
    Place: Essaouira. The manuscript is written in Hebrew and French and includes the stamp of Avraham Ben Shoshan (Abraham Bensoussan in French).
  - Document with regard to real estate of a man who is a resident of Amizmiz, 1881; MS.1825.0906; 4 pages (1 blank); 15 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 14)
    Place: Essaouira. Signed by Masud Azencot and Yosef ben Yaakov Hadad.
  - Document concerning the sale of a house, 1900; MS.1825.1044; 1 leaf; 23 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Testimony in court, 1844; MS.1825.1101; 1 leaf; 17 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 15)
    Place: El Jadida/Mazagan.
  - Letter regarding a debt of money, 1872; MS.1825.1108; 1 leaf; 23 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Two certificates issued by the court: a birth certificate and a confirmation of a birth date of a couple's son, 1931; MS.1825.1172.1-.2; 4 pages; 25 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 16)
    Place: Essaouira. A birth certificate has the stamp of Avraham Ben Shoshan (Abraham Bensoussan), president of the rabbinic court of Mogador. Signed by Isaac Benchimol (Ben Shimol), 1931. The same tribunal gave a certificate that a couple was married and their son was born in 1895. They are both issued by the same court, written in Hebrew with a French translation underneath.
  - Legal document regarding a loan of money, 1917; MS.1825.1173; 2 pages; 21 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Business letter, 1922; MS.1825.1174; 1 leaf; 13 x 21 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Letter requesting financial assistance from Mogador, 1888; MS.1825.1180; 4 pages (3 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Friendly letter in Judeo-Arabic from Yaakov Afriat, Circa 1900-circa 1920; MS.1825.1213; 1 leaf; 26 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Letter in Judeo-Arabic from Yaakov Afriat with regard to commercial affairs, 1911; MS.1825.1218; 2 leaves; 26 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Copy of a gift document, 1954; MS.1825.1336; 2 pages; 30 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 19)
    Place: Essaouira. Avraham Rosilio, who wrote the document, changed the conditions of the gift. Signed by Ya'ish Suissa and Yitshak [?]. Certified by Mosheh Vizman with the stamp of the rabbinical court of Essaouira.
  - Letter containing a liturgical poem sent from Essaouira to Tangier, 1894; MS.1825.1522; 4 pages (2 blank); 21 centimeters. (Box 18, Folder 19)
    Place: Essaouira. The letter was written by Yosef ha-Levi and sent to Mosheh Toledano. The poem is a harsh protest against the rich. The letter is written in Hebrew.
- Casablanca, Circa 1800-1965; Series VIII
  Series VIII consists of documents, letters, testimony and certificates from the port city of Casablanca, as well as Jadīdah (El Jadida, Mazagan), Settat, and Beni Mellal. Casablanca is a relatively new city, established only in the nineteenth century. As it grew into a large metropolis, it attracted Jews from all over Morocco. By 1920 its Jewish population numbered about 100,000 making it the largest Jewish community in Morocco. In the early 20th century Casablanca become a center of Jewish learning and scholarship. The documents in this series relate to inheritance, financial matters, communal institutions, marriage, divorce, and other matters. Oversize documents from Casablanca are in Box 35.
  - Collection of various texts, perhaps by a school teacher, Circa 1900-circa 1920; MS.1825.0016; 162 pages; 32 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Place: Mazagan?. Notebook containing about twenty different texts. The most important one is Luah 'ibur, which means calendar, written in Moroccan Judeo-Arabic as a series of questions and answers. A second important group of texts are lists of Hebrew words translated to Judeo-Arabic. There are at least two such glossaries in this volume. There are also lists of students in Talmud Torah. It is likely that the writer of this notebook was a school teacher. On pages 32a there is a signature dated Oct. 1, 1916 of Masʻud ben Shitrit, probably from the community of Mazagan. This may very well be the teacher.
  - Document concerning inheritance, 1922; MS.1825.0039; 1 leaf; 18 x 21 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 2)
    Place: Casablanca. Declaration of a dying woman concerning what she would leave as an inheritance. Signed by the rabbinic judges of Casablanca.
  - Halikhot Sheva by Simon Baruch Ohayon, Circa 1930-circa 1955; MS.1825.0041; 12 pages; 35 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 3)
    Place: Casablanca?. Unknown text written as a letter to the rabbinic judge, Yosef ha-Laḥmi of Agadir. The subject is a man who moved from one city to another and the resulting dispute with his wife. Ohayon quotes rabbinic authorities, both from medieval times and from modern Morocco. His Hebrew is a combination of rabbinic style and modern Hebrew style. This unknown Ohayon seems to be a sage from one of the big cities of Morocco from the second third of the twentieth century.
  - Rabbinic document concerning inheritance, 1840; MS.1825.0068; 1 leaf; 35 centimeters. Partly torn. (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Place: Jadīdah (Mazagan). Rabbinic document from the city Jadīdah (Mazagan) concerning a dispute over the inheritance of 'A. Ben-Wa'ish, originally from the community of Azemmour. Rabbi Ben-Wa'ish of Jadīdah decided to divide the inheritance between his family and the poor people in the community. The decision is signed by Elazar Hazzan and Aharon Almalih, was confirmed by Masʻud Ben Moha and Mosheh Pinto, and re-confirmed in 1870 in Azemmour by Yitshak ben Elazar.
  - Letter from Shimon Shabbitai (Simon Schabitai) to Rabbi Zaguri in the city of Mazagan, 1923; MS.1825.0415; 1 leaf; 25 centimeters. The document is torn in two along the middle fold. (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Place: Mazagan. Letter includes wishes for the New Year and the Festival of Succot.
  - Letter with regard to a delayed marriage, 1952; MS.1825.0419; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Place: Mazagan. The letter was sent from Shelomoh Zaguri to Shemuel Ha-Kohen.
  - Letter from Shelomoh Zaguri with regard to a marriage, 1951; MS.1825.0420; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Place: Mazagan. The city Taourirt in Northeastern Morocco is mentioned.
  - Letter with regard to the right of a certain woman to live in Eastern Morocco, 1951; MS.1825.0421; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Place: Mazagan. The letter is from Shelomoh Zaguri to Shemuel Ha-Kohen in Eastern Morocco.
  - Letter from Shelomoh ha-Kohen of Mazagan regarding assistance in the printing of one of his books, 1938; MS.1825.0435; 2 pages; 28 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Document of betrothal written by Shelomoh ha-Kohen Zaguri, 1950; MS.1825.0445; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 6)
    Place: Mazagan. The young woman is from the city of Debdou. The letter expresses reservations with regard to living in the city of Taourirt.
  - Letter from Settat to Casablanca written by Yosef Shalom Malka to Avraham Shimon Hadida, 1949; MS.1825.0449; 2 pages; 31 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 6)
    Place: Settat. The topic is mundane, but the use of language is interesting. In Judeo-Arabic.
  - Legal decision with regard to guardianship, 1965; MS.1825.0454; 2 pages; 27 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 7)
    Place: Casablanca. Signed by Shimon Abihasira and [Avraham Maman Saadon?] and confirmed by Shalom Mesas, the presiding judge.
  - Letter by Yitshak Gershon Kohen with a confirmation of Avraham Yifrah, 1917; MS.1825.0456; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 7)
    Place: Casablanca. The letter was sent to Yeudah Ben Shimol.
  - Letter in Moroccan Judeo-Arabic requesting financial support for publication of a newspaper, Circa 1800-circa 1850; MS.1825.0481; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 8)
    Place: Casablanca. The document appears to be from Casablanca.
  - Document signed by David ben Mosheh Azulai and Shimon Kohen, 1850; MS.1825.0545; 4 pages (2 blank); 20 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 8)
    Place: Casablanca.
  - Testimony regarding the sale of a synagogue's supply of oil and candles, 1898; MS.1825.0566; 4 pages (3 blank); 23 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 8)
    Place: Casablanca. In 1892 Mosheh Yifrah, the cantor of the synagogue, had sold to Yosef ben Meir Elkaim and Yosef ben Avraham Shriki large amounts of olive oil and fifty kilos of candles. The testimony states that he did not benefit in any way himself, but sold the supplies to buy lamps for the synagogue. The document is written partly in Hebrew, but mostly in Judeo-Arabic. Signed by Suliman ben Yitshak Sabbah and Yaakov Alzam.
  - Document regarding misuse of charitable funds, 1898; MS.1825.0567; 2 pages; 36 centimeters. (Box 35, Folder 1)
    Place: Casablanca. According to this document, the wealthy leader of Tangier, Yahya Ben Assayag, donated funds to Masud Izarzar for the benefit of widows, orphans, and the poor, but Izarzar kept the funds for himself. The document is signed by dozens of members of the community of Casablanca (Dār al-Bayḍāʼ), including: Sliman ben Yitshak Sabbah, Yaakov Elzam, and Masud Ohana.
  - Letter in Judeo-Arabic sent from Casablanca to Yitshak ibn Tsur, 1910; MS.1825.0699; 2 pages; 28 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Letter concerning a sum of money, 1918; MS.1825.0744; 1 leaf; 25 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 9)
    Place: Casablanca. Letter to Mordekhai Amar in Casblanca with regard to a sum of money sent by [Refael ben Shemayah?] in Rabat.
  - Letter with regard to alimony and child support, 1930; MS.1825.0745; 1 leaf; 25 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 9)
    Place: Casablanca. Letter to Rabbi Elyakim in Casablanca by Rahel bat Avraham with regard to David Biton, who does not support her or the children.
  - Letter from the chief rabbi Meir Elkaim to Refael Attia in Rabat with a demand that Eliyahu Biton be returned to his home, 1922; MS.1825.0746; 1 leaf; 31 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Letter from the chief rabbi Meir Elkaim to Refael Attia in Rabat with a demand that Eliyahu Biton be returned to his home, 1920s?; MS.1825.0747; 1 leaf; 31 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - French certification of a document, 1929; MS.1825.0748 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    Place: Casablanca. A French document that validates another document signed by the head of the rabbinic court in Casablanca. Includes the stamp of the head of the rabbinic court, Meir Hai Elyakim. The top half of the page appears to be missing.
  - Summons to a rabbinic court to David Zaguri who was accused of starving his wife, 1921; MS.1825.0749; 1 leaf; 31 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 10)
    Place: Casablanca. Signed by the rabbinic court of Casablanca.
  - Summons to rabbinic court to Eliahu ben David Yosef who is being sued by his wife, 1929; MS.1825.0750; 4 pages (3 blanks); 31 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 11)
    Place: Casablanca. Letter from the rabbinic court in Casablanca to the rabbinic court in Rabat with regard to a man by the name of Eliahu ben David Yosef who is being sued by his wife. He had already received one summons and did not appear.
  - Annulment of marriage, 1922; MS.1825.0751; 1 leaf; 27 centimeters. (Box 19, Folder 11)
    Place: Casablanca. A letter issued by the rabbinic court telling a man that his marriage is annulled. Signed by Hayim Yosef Maman.